<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
      <channel>
        <language>en</language>
        <title>Yle News | Tuoreimmat uutiset</title>
        <description>Yle News | Tuoreimmat uutiset</description>
        <link>https://yle.fi/uutiset/news/</link>
        <atom:link href="https://feeds-production-lb.c2.yle.fi/uutiset/v1/recent.rss?publisherIds=YLE_NEWS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <category>Tuoreimmat uutiset</category>
        <item>
          <title>Finnair strike could snarl ski holiday travel plans</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305883?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The Transport Workers’ Union threatens a strike from 22 February until 8 March, during the school vacation period.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The Transport Workers’ Union (AKT) has filed a strike warning with the service sector employers&#39; group Palta regarding Finnair cabin crew members.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The union is threatening a strike from 22 February until 8 March, when most schools have winter breaks known as ski holidays. Traditionally many families from populous southern and central Finland travel to Lapland, southern Europe or beyond during the staggered vacation weeks.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The AKT said on Monday that the walkout would cover all work covered by the collective agreement, beginning early on Tuesday, 22 February – unless an agreement is reached before then.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Most schools in southern Finland are on winter break 19-27 February, followed by most in central Finland 26 Feb-6 March and eastern and northern areas 5-13 March.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">AKT "regrets inconvenience to passengers"</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;The situation is unfortunate, and the AKT regrets the inconvenience to passengers. However, the cuts in pay and working conditions required by Finnair are so unreasonable that they cannot be accepted,&quot; AKT President <strong class="yle__article__strong">Ismo Kokko</strong> said in a statement on Monday.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The union said it &quot;understands that the coronavirus pandemic has hit airlines quite hard&quot;, but argues that &quot;employees have already played their part&quot; in the form of furloughs and various austerity measures.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The AKT, which is part of the blue-collar federation SAK, has some 45,000 members. It is also staging <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12282187">support actions</a> for striking UPM paper workers.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Palta is one of the biggest member associations within the Confederation of Finnish Industries (EK), representing more than 2,000 service-sector firms.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 17:57:00 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>talous</category><category>Finnair</category><category>matkailu</category><category>liikenne</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305883</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/13-3-7163570.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Survey: Growing dissatisfaction with Covid restrictions in Finland</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305931?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Approval of the handling of the crisis has waned, but confidence in health institute THL has remained fairly steady since last May.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">People in Finland are less satisfied with how the government has handled the coronavirus crisis than they were about eight months ago, according to findings from two surveys carried out by Åbo Akademi University in Turku.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Last month around 38 percent of respondents said they thought the government&#39;s measures to prevent the spread of coronavirus were well-balanced between public health and economic concerns. However, a similar survey carried out in May found nearly half of the respondents said the same.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The respondents&#39; answers have become more polarised since May — with respondents increasingly either very critical or very positive.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In general, men tended to be more critical than women, while the oldest age groups were the most supportive of coronavirus restrictions.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Leaders and institutions</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Approximately 43 percent of respondents in the most recent survey found the coronavirus-related restrictions in place last month were reasonable, while a majority found that the rules were either too strict or not stringent enough.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The survey also examined people&#39;s attitudes about how political leaders and institutions have handled the crisis.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">There was very little change in people&#39;s attitudes toward the Institute for Health and Welfare (THL), which has helped to lead policymakers&#39; decisions about restrictions and other measures.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In May, around 19 percent of respondents said they thought the THL had acted &quot;very well&quot; in the crisis. Last month that proportion dipped slightly to 17 percent. The vast majority, 62 and 61 percent respectively in each survey, said THL had acted &quot;fairly well.&quot;</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Dip in satisfaction for PM</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Meanwhile, approval of efforts by Prime Minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Sanna Marin</strong> (SDP) efforts during the pandemic dropped, with 26 percent saying she acted &quot;very well&quot; during the crisis in May and just 18 percent saying the same last month.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">At the other end of the spectrum, increasing numbers of respondents said they considered the PM&#39;s epidemic-related actions to be &quot;very poor,&quot; or the lowest on the scale, with 16 percent saying so in May and 22 percent saying that last month. However, 39 and 37 percent of respondents (respectively) said they thought Marin was doing a &quot;fairly good&quot; job.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">One minister in particular saw increased approval over the eight-month period. In May, just six percent of respondents said the Minister of Family Affairs and Social Services, <strong class="yle__article__strong">Krista Kiuru</strong>, was doing a &quot;very good&quot; job but that proportion jumped to 11 percent in January. Kiuru began maternity leave in early January.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The survey was carried out by Åbo Akademi on its web-based polling platform kansalaismielipide.fi. About 4,000 respondents took part in the survey between 18 and 21 January 2022. The findings of the new survey were compared to a previous poll carried out 7-16 May 2021.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 16:51:00 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>COVID-19</category><category>koronavirus</category><category>rajoitukset</category><category>Marinin hallitus</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305931</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/13-3-11650043.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Civil disobedience tactics divide opinion among politicians </title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305432?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Finland's Interior Minister Krista Mikkonen sees civil disobedience as an acceptable means to bring about change, but not all political leaders agree.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Interior Minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Krista Mikkonen</strong> (Green) believes that civil disobedience is one way for activists to make an impact, but says protesters must always take responsibility for their actions, and that there is no room for violence or vandalism.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Over the weekend, hundreds of protesters taking part in the &quot;Convoy Finland 2022&quot; demonstration, blocked the main street in front of the Finnish Parliament in Helsinki before <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12303909">being dispersed by police</a>. Up to 150 of the protesters&#39; vehicles were on hand, some of which were towed away. Police arrested 55 people during the demonstration on Friday and a further 15 on Saturday. No arrests were reported on Sunday.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to <strong class="yle__article__strong">Niko Pyrhönen</strong>, a researcher at the University of Helsinki, civil disobedience seems to be attracting growing numbers of people.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Blocking streets, causing a general disturbance and creating some kind of spectacle-like event is a very effective way to politicise issues and bring them into the public debate,&quot; Pyrhönen points out.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Growing trend</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">When one group gets attention through civil disobedience, it encourages others to follow suit, according to Pyrhönen.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In December, climate activists from the Elokapina protest movement — the Finnish branch of the environmental group Extinction Rebellion — received extensive media coverage after <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12226292">blocking traffic</a> on the same main thoroughfare. This was the most recent, but not the first such action by the group. At that time, police detained 38 protestors after they refused to move to an alternative location.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Demonstrations and the disruptions they cause divide opinion among the general public. Leading politicians also disagree on how civil disobedience can be used to influence society.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Interior Minister Mikkonen sees civil disobedience as an acceptable means of protest, within reasonable limits.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I think it is an acceptable way to act when it&#39;s done soberly, in one&#39;s own name and one&#39;s own face and each person carries responsibility for their actions,&quot; Mikkonen says.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to Mikkonen, taking responsibility means accepting that non-compliance with police orders or breaking the law will result in sanctions and penalties.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Opposing view</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The vice-chair of the opposition National Coalition Party former justice minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Antti Häkkänen</strong>, shies away from endorsing the use of civil disobedience by protesters.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Police orders, and the law, must always be obeyed,&quot; Häkkänen tells Yle.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to Häkkänen, Finland has a very broad legal framework for demonstrations. He believes that this should be enough for actions by groups such as Elokapina and the supporters of Convoy Finland.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In turn, he points out, the police have the duty to provide the opportunity to demonstrate within the framework of the law.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;In Finland, everyone has the right to demonstrate, but the police also have a duty to ensure the safety of society and the safety of bystanders. That is why the police orders must be followed,&quot; Häkkänen says.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Häkkänen says that he understands that political and societal pressures can create a need for demonstrations.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">However, he adds, &quot;It is the machinery of democracy that makes decisions, not the cheering of crowds.&quot;</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">in Häkkänen&#39;s opinion, this must be taken into account when considering demonstrations and the rules that govern them.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 15:54:26 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>politiikka</category><category>kotimaa</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305432</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-8757066183f78e3df0f.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Editors to protesters: Let reporters do their job</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305660?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Following harassment of journalists at the weekend Convoy demonstration in Helsinki, Finland's Association of Editors has issued a reminder that the media is not a party to protests.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In a statement issued on Monday, Finland&#39;s Association of Editors (PTY) points out that the media is not a party to protests, and that both demonstrations and a freely functioning media are elements of a democratic society.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Reporters covering the Convoy Finland 2022 protests in central Helsinki this past weekend said they faced<a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12304211"> verbal and physical harassment </a>as they went about their jobs. According to the Association of Editors the harassment was particularly experienced by camera crews and journalists providing live coverage. On Friday, protestors stole microphones twice from an Iltalehti reporter, and tried to do the same to Yle reporters.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;It is in everyone&#39;s interest for journalists to be able to do their work in peace, and report on both the demands of the demonstrations and the course of events. Only professional media reach the entire audience,&quot; <strong class="yle__article__strong">Minna Holopainen</strong>, the chair of PTY and the editor-in-chief of the Finnish news agency STT, stated in a press release.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to PTY, respect for the work and safety of others is a part of Finnish culture. The association says it hopes that situations like the incidents at the weekend protest will not be seen again.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;We call on organisers of all demonstrations to take into account the possibility for the media to work and to encourage participants to act appropriately. In this way the messages of the protests will be conveyed to the public,&quot; said Holopainen.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">On Sunday, the president of the Union of Journalists in Finland, <strong class="yle__article__strong">Hanne Aho</strong>, also commented on the reports of harassment, tweeting that it is in everyone&#39;s interest that journalists can do their work at demonstrations without the risk of violence and intimidation.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Police silent about organiser</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Helsinki police have declined to disclose any information about the organiser of the Convoy Finland 2022 demonstration over the weekend, citing privacy legislation .</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to the Helsinki police communications office, the organiser of the demonstration is a private individual. Police say that under the terms of the Act on the Openness of Government Activities the organiser of a protest can be named only if it is an organisation, association or other legal entity.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The communications office added that this interpretation of the law and police policy on disclosure are now under review.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 14:58:54 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>kotimaa</category><category>rikokset</category><category>media</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305660</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91089261fda82e034af.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Corrupt ex-drug squad chief released from prison to supervised probation</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305541?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Jari Aarnio, whose murder conviction was overturned on Friday, has been released from prison wearing an ankle monitor.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><strong class="yle__article__strong">Jari Aarnio</strong>, the disgraced former head of the Helsinki Police narcotics unit, has been released from prison under supervised probation. The move was confirmed by his lawyer, <strong class="yle__article__strong">Riitta Leppiniemi</strong>.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Aarnio&#39;s location is being tracked by an ankle monitor. Under supervised probation, convicts are only allowed to move around in certain areas. They must also remain drug-free and comply with other conditions imposed on them.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Aarnio&#39;s murder conviction was <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12302025">overturned</a> on Friday. In December 2020, Helsinki District Court sentenced him to a life in prison for murder. In Finland, a &quot;life term&quot; typically lasts 11-13 years.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The case was related to the 2003 killing of a Swedish-Turkish man, <strong class="yle__article__strong">Volkan Ünsal</strong>, in Helsinki. Unlike the district court, the Court of Appeal held that Aarnio had no precise information about the plans to assassinate Ünsal or that the victim was in imminent danger. According to the appeals court, Aarnio did not appear to know when, where or how Ünsal was to be killed.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Contrary to the judgment of the District Court, the appeals court also ruled that Aarnio did not have any special legal obligation to prevent a felony, as alleged in the indictment and required for a charge of official negligence.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In December, the Helsinki Court of Appeal released Aarnio from pre-trial detention in connection with the murder charge, but he still remained in prison due to previous drug convictions.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In the summer of 2019, Aarnio received a ten-year sentence for a case involving the importation of hashish. He was convicted of, among other things, several serious drug offences and gross misrepresentation of evidence.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 13:53:21 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>rikokset</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305541</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-7496185fc8ccb87eef7.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>National Audit Office moves to fire Yli-Viikari</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305375?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The National Audit Office sees a particularly compelling reason for Yli-Viikari to be the dismissed as Director General.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The National Audit Office of Finland (VTV) is taking measures to dismiss <strong class="yle__article__strong">Tytti Yli-Viikari</strong> from the position of Director General. Yli-Viikari is currently suspended from the post.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">She was also dismissed from her other role as Auditor General by Parliament last summer.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The National Audit Office sees a particularly compelling reason for Yli-Viikari to be dismissed as Director General under the State Civil Service Act. It will therefore initiate proceedings to dismiss her from the post. Yli-Viikari will be consulted before the matter is resolved.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The prosecutor has expressed dissatisfaction with the <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12292381">district court&#39;s decision</a> to fine Yli-Viikari after finding her guilty of misconduct in a public office and malfeasance in a public office.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Yli-Viikari and VTV have also expressed their dissatisfaction with the court&#39;s ruling.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Criminal proceedings still pending</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The decision of the district court is not final, and criminal proceedings are still pending. Therefore, the Audit Office has taken measures to continue the suspension of Yli-Viikari and <strong class="yle__article__strong">Mikko Koiranen</strong>, the office&#39;s Director of Administration. They were both found to have allowed a third VTV official to receive a salary for two years without doing any work.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">After hearing from all parties, VTV will decide whether the conditions have been met to continue the suspension of both and to permanently dismiss Yli-Viikari.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In late December, Parliament approved the appointment of <strong class="yle__article__strong">Sami Yläoutinen</strong> as the new Auditor General and head of the National Audit Office for a five-year term that began on 1 January.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 12:52:53 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>rikokset</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305375</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-89219061b99e44bee69.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Omicron subvariant set to become dominant source of Covid cases in Helsinki region</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305414?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The spread of the subvariant is however unlikely to lead to an overburdening of healthcare services, according to HUS Director of Diagnostics Lasse Lehtonen.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Currently about one in ten Covid infections detected in the Helsinki and Uusimaa hospital district (HUS) are caused by the Omicron BA.2 subvariant.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">However, while the more commonly known BA.1 variant is responsible for about 90 percent of cases in the capital region, that share is rapidly receding, according to the district&#39;s Director of Diagnostics, <strong class="yle__article__strong">Lasse Lehtonen</strong>.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The incidence of subvariant cases, which was first detected in the HUS region last week, are becoming increasingly more prevalent.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;The BA.2 variant may be the main variant in the HUS area within one month,&quot; Lehtonen said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The subvariant has spread rapidly in Denmark and Norway. In the vast majority of cases it causes very mild illness, especially in people who are fully vaccinated. However, it spreads faster and more easily than its predecessor.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The Omicron variant has caused a peak in infection rates. Public health authority THL registered nearly 20,000 cases over the past weekend.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to Lehtonen, the rapid spread of the BA.2 subvariant is likely to prolong the current wave of infections somewhat longer than expected, but he does not think this will lead to an overburdening of healthcare services.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;At HUS, the situation has further improved compared to last week. There are now 10 Covid patients in intensive care units, which is more than half as much as in mid-January. Of course, the BA.2 variant could mean that the Covid IC units are not cleared as quickly as we would like,&quot; he added.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 12:31:26 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>COVID-19</category><category>terveys</category><category>Helsinki</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305414</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-90130861dff74e5a3f8.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Police lose hacked therapy centre criminal reports after spreadsheet error</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305218?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The patient records of about 30,000 people were stolen when Vastaamo's database was hacked on at least two separate occasions.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Helsinki police admit they have lost some of the criminal reports from the wide-scale hacking of patient records from a psychotherapy centre, and have not made efforts to contact victims to inform them about the mistake.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Officers say the reports were lost when they were moved from a spreadsheet into the police system.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The hacking of privately-run psychotherapy centre Vastaamo&#39;s client database was first <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-11605460">revealed</a> on 21 October 2020, when the patient data of tens of thousands of people was stolen and used to blackmail both the company and the patients.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Investigating officers asked each victim to file a criminal report, and by February 2021 <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-11801245">more than 25,000 such reports</a> had been submitted. The majority of the reports were filed at Pasila police station in Helsinki, but others were filed elsewhere around the country.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The sheer volume of reports caused congestion within the police&#39;s systems, and it was nearly a year before the police followed up to ask the victims to fill in a statement online, as they did not have the resources to interview every patient individually. The statement form was available to anyone who had submitted a criminal report.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">However, due to a file error on an Excel spreadsheet, some of the criminal reports had not been completed and were therefore not received into the police&#39;s system.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I noticed by chance that the statement form can be filled in online. But when I logged in to the police&#39;s online service, it turned out I didn’t have access to that form,&quot; one former Vastaamo client, who wished to remain anonymous, told Svenska Yle.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">She had filed a criminal report in Pasila police station at the end of October 2020.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;After several days of trying in vain to find someone who could help me, I went to Pasila police station again,&quot; she said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">By then it was the middle of January 2022, some 14 or 15 months since she had filed her initial criminal report. She had not heard from or received any instructions from the police since then.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The existence of the form to make a statement had not been widely publicised by police.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Staff at Pasila police station searched for the woman&#39;s criminal report in the police&#39;s system, but she was to receive a nasty surprise instead.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Excel problems</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;They couldn&#39;t find a criminal report in my name. Therefore, they registered a new criminal report. In addition, I received the name and contact details of the person in charge of the preliminary investigation. I emailed him,&quot; she explained.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">No one at Pasila police station understood what had gone wrong, but the officer who led the pre-trial investigation was able to reveal what had happened.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;He said that not all reports were recorded directly into the police&#39;s information system, as thousands had been made over a short period of time,&quot; she said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><em class="yle__article__emphasis">Story continues after the photo.</em></p>
<figure class="yle__article__figure"><img class="yle__article__figure__image" width=960 height=640 src="//images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload/w_960,h_640/39-5082225b924cb834a56.jpg" alt="Helsingin pääpoliisiasema Pasilassa"><figcaption class="yle__article__figure__caption"><span class="yle__article__figure__caption__text">Thousands of criminal reports related to the Vastaamo hacking were filed at Pasila police station within a couple of days. </span><span class="yle__article__figure__caption__source">Carolina Husu / Yle</span></figcaption></figure>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Instead of a database, the criminal reports were recorded via Microsoft Excel files. Some of the files turned out to be unreadable when police tried to transfer them in the official system. The cause of the problem is unknown.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Detective Inspector <strong class="yle__article__strong">Jari Illukka</strong> from the Helsinki police department told Svenska Yle that about a dozen criminal reports have disappeared from Excel, but the exact number is not known.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police did not consider it necessary to report the blunder, Illukka said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;No one&#39;s legal rights have been threatened, because at this stage of the investigation, people have to fill in an electronic statement form in any case. It is necessary if you want to keep making progress,&quot; he said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The form must be completed if victims want to receive damages in any possible future lawsuit. No form, no refund.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">This means that from the police&#39;s point of view, any mistakes will come to light at some point-</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">So you think this is good enough, Svenska Yle asked.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Yes,&quot; Illukka replied.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">One third of victims filled in form</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police estimate that the records of more than 30,000 people were stolen during the Vastaamo data breach, and more than 22,000 of these victims have since reported the crime.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">However, just over three thousand statement forms had been submitted to police by the end of January, or one in ten victims.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">This suggests that some of those whose criminal reports have not been recorded due to the Excel error may not have been notified of the disappearance of their criminal reports.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><strong class="yle__article__strong">Marko Leponen</strong>, who is leading the investigation on behalf of the National Bureau of Investigation (NBI), conceded to Yle that 3,000 statements from 30,000 victims was a very small amount, but wondered if this could be due to a lack of awareness among victims of the need to submit a statement via the online portal.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><em class="yle__article__emphasis">Story continues after the photo.</em></p>
<figure class="yle__article__figure"><img class="yle__article__figure__image" width=960 height=640 src="//images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload/w_960,h_640/39-5551275caded2d120b4.jpg" alt="keskusrikospoliisin kyberrikostorjuntakeskuksen rikoskomisario Marko Leponen"><figcaption class="yle__article__figure__caption"><span class="yle__article__figure__caption__text">Marko Leponen of the National Bureau of Investigation.</span><span class="yle__article__figure__caption__source">Juha Kivioja / Yle</span></figcaption></figure>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The form can still be submitted, although police initially said the deadline was 31 January.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;It was a little misleading to say that it was the last day to fill out the form. It was about how much resources we spend tracking the forms. If it turns out that the number of forms is increasing, we can review the process again,&quot; Leponen said.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Many have "lost hope"</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Victim Support Finland (RIKU) has helped many people affected by the Vastaamo data breach, and Regional Director <strong class="yle__article__strong">Elina Viitasaari</strong> told Yle she deplores the apparent disappearance of criminal reports.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Of course it&#39;s unfortunate. I cannot take a strong position on the activities of the police, but the number of victims was so large that it has certainly been a challenge for the information system,&quot; Viitasaari said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">She urged people who need help to <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.riku.fi/en/contact-information/">contact</a> Victim Support Finland, and also said she hopes as many victims as possible will fill out the online statement form. However, she also understands why many people are tired of the entire affair.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I think some have made a statement, but have lost all hope of receiving compensation. We still recommend filing a criminal report and filling out the [statement] form,&quot; she said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Viitasaari added that cooperation between the police and other services has worked well during the preliminary investigation.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">"How is it possible?"</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The woman interviewed by Svenska Yle said she is disappointed with the police and is upset that she has almost been left out of the process.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In October 2020, she received a paper from a police station that was supposed to be a copy of her criminal report. When it was examined in more detail in January this year, few of the details were correct. For example, her name was misspelled.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I do not understand how it is possible that I have received a copy of a criminal report that does not exist and the registration number of a report, which also does not appear to exist and which, moreover, is in the wrong format. I assumed, of course, that the copy meant the report had already been registered,&quot; she said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I also do not understand why they [the police] have not informed us about this matter. It would have been logical to inform people about it, at least when they opened access to the statement form. They could have said that if your form is not found, you will need to contact the police and file a new criminal report, as it may be that the first report was never recorded,&quot; she added.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Loss of a criminal report is rare</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Detective Inspector Illukka told Yle that the disappearance of criminal reports is rare. However, the Vastaamo case is exceptional as thousands of people came to police stations to file their reports. Most criminal reports today are filed online.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Criminal reports do not usually disappear, as a large majority are made online. Criminal reports made at the station are usually entered directly into the system,&quot; he said, adding that police are learning from what happened and are currently developing their working processes.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The police&#39;s goal, he said, is that even large numbers of reports can be securely registered in a short period of time.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 11:18:42 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>rikokset</category><category>kotimaa</category><category>terveys</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305218</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-7362685f9bbd6328f97.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Finns Party to submit no confidence motion over fuel, electricity prices </title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305147?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Finns Party chair Riikka Purra says rising prices are significantly weakening the purchasing power of low and middle-income earners.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The opposition Finns Party has announced it will file an interpellation, the first move towards a vote of no confidence in the government of Prime Minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Sanna Marin</strong> (SDP), over the issue of fuel and electricity prices and what it views as the government&#39;s inability to react to the situation.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to Finns Party chair <strong class="yle__article__strong">Riikka Purra</strong>, <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12271493">rising prices</a> are impacting the costs of transport and housing and will significantly weaken the purchasing power of low and middle-income earners.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Worry and wonder is not enough anymore. Citizens need a vision of how the situation will be alleviated,&quot; Purra stated in a tweet in Finnish.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The Finns Party leader further condemned a recent statement by Minister of Finance <strong class="yle__article__strong">Annika Saarikko</strong> (Cen) during parliamentary question time who said that those struggling with high electricity bills can turn to social services for help.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to Purra, the Finns Party considers that reply to be arrogant.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;We demand national measures to reduce fuel and electricity prices, such as tax cuts. The government is spreading its hands, blaming world market prices, and claiming they can do nothing about it. This is not true,&quot; Purra said in a party press release.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Purra argues that the government&#39;s climate policy is exacerbating the situation.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;The government must back away from a carbon neutrality target that is stricter than in other countries. Finns cannot be oppressed by the climate from two directions, both by overblown national measures, and by agreeing to everything that the EU dares to propose,&quot; she continued.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The other main opposition party, the National Coalition, is also reported to be considering backing the Finns Party&#39;s interpellation. Movement Now indicated on Monday that they will join the interpellation, according to a report by Centre Party newspaper Suomenmaa.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 10:25:45 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>talous</category><category>politiikka</category><category>ilmasto</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305147</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-90533861ed8dc30abc7.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Monday's papers: Latest Nato poll, Convoy protest winds down, a break from blizzards</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12305027?origin=rss</link>
          <description>A new poll by Maaseudun Tulevaisuus suggests that nearly half of people in Finland are in favour of joining Nato, if the nation's leaders were to recommend membership.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">A fresh poll commissioned and published by the farmers&#39; union paper <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.maaseuduntulevaisuus.fi/politiikka/artikkeli-1.1772691">Maaseudun Tulevaisuus </a>found that 45 percent of those surveyed would support <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12279231">Finland applying to join Nato</a>, on the condition that membership were recommended by the nation&#39;s leaders.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Roughly one third of respondents opposed the proposition, while just under one quarter were undecided.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Backing for Nato membership in this poll was highest among voters who identified as supporters of the opposition National Coalition Party and Prime Minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Sanna Marin</strong>&#39;s Social Democratic Party. A majority of supporters of both parties were ready to back membership, if proposed by the national leadership. The highest level of opposition was among supporters of the Left Alliance, a clear majority of whom would oppose the move.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The MT poll also showed divisions along the lines of gender, socioeconomic status and age. Some 56 percent of men said they would support joining Nato if the national leadership recommended it. Only 34 percent of women took the same position. Support for Nato membership was highest among those over 64. Higher levels of support for membership showed a positive correlation with income, with higher earners more likely to be in favour of joining the alliance.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Regionally, people in the capital region and in rural municipalities had the most favourable views on Nato membership.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">MT’s survey of 1,030 people was carried out by Kantar TNS Agri.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Convoy protest falls flat</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">After kicking off Friday with rowdy demonstrations and traffic disruptions, a protest in central Helsinki billed as &quot;Convoy Finland 2022&quot; consisted of a handful of individuals and an orderly procession of some 15 cars and vans by Sunday evening, <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.is.fi/kotimaa/art-2000008593681.html">reports Ilta-Sanomat</a>.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Helsinki police said that Sunday&#39;s demonstration ended without incident by half past eleven. Organisers have told police they plan to continue the protest daily from 10 am to 10 pm.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police arrested 55 people during <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12304211">the demonstration on Friday</a> and a further 15 on Saturday. No arrests were reported on Sunday.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Protesters&#39; demands include the end of all Covid-related restrictions in Finland, a 50 percent reduction in fuel taxes, and the resignation of the current government.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In an <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.is.fi/paakirjoitus/art-2000008593560.html">editorial commentary</a> on the protests, Ilta-Sanomat argues that demonstrators should have given the goals and means more thought.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The paper agrees that Covid restrictions have disrupted ordinary life and strained nerves, and this is a matter of concern. Fuel prices have been rising on world markets, something which is also affecting many people in Finland.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The paper points out though that Covid restrictions and the price of petrol have nothing to do with each other, and blocking traffic in front of an empty parliament building on the weekends will not lead to the resignation of the government.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Ilta-Sanomat then asks how useful it is to make grandiose demands in a way that only annoys most citizens, &quot;Do we have to copy every protest we see online from abroad?&quot;</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">New Baltic ferry</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In news that may be an indication of a coming revival in holiday travel, several papers, including<a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.hs.fi/talous/art-2000008593162.html"> Helsingin Sanomat</a>, report Sunday&#39;s arrival in Turku of the Viking Line&#39;s new car-passenger ferry Viking Glory.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Built in China, the ship will start operating on the Turku-Mariehamn-Stockholm route in early March.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to Viking Line, the new vessel consumes up to ten percent less fuel than the smaller Viking Grace, which at one time was considered world&#39;s most environmentally-friendly ship of its type. Viking Glory uses sulphur-free liquefied natural gas and will also use biogas.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Break from blizzards</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Tampere&#39;s <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.aamulehti.fi/saa/art-2000008593199.html">Aamulehti</a> reports a respite from snowfall from for the beginning of the week, at least in the Pirkanmaa, Häme and Uusimaa regions. It reports Finnish Meteorological Institute forecasting some brief periods of snowfall on Tuesday, but nothing like the blizzards in recent days.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The paper also reports a large number of weather-related traffic accidents over the weekend.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to<a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.iltalehti.fi/saauutiset/a/d9f570b6-1812-49f0-a505-670fa7908093"> Iltalehti</a>, Monday&#39;s temperatures should be at or above the freezing point in southern and southwestern parts of the country. Warming temperatures are likely to make roads and pavements slippery for drivers and pedestrians alike.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 09:16:33 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>ulkopolitiikka</category><category>COVID-19</category><category>matkailu</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12305027</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91090461fda849aefcb.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Finland's Convoy protest weekend enters third day</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12304724?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The protests have shrunk over the course of the weekend.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Finland&#39;s Convoy protest had shrunk to a small group on Sunday evening, occupying a square close to parliament but not blocking traffic.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The protesters had demanded cheaper petrol, an end to Covid restrictions and vaccine mandates, and the resignation of the government.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In pursuit of these goals they gathered on Friday evening and blocked traffic outside parliament, refusing to disperse when asked by police. Some 55 were detained on Friday night and another 15 were taken to the cells on Saturday evening.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">With temperatures hovering around zero and heavy snow falling all weekend, some had driven saunas on trailers to the protest site, and the event took on a carnival atmosphere — although there was aggression directed at police and reporters.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">By Sunday the protester seemed to have lost enthusiasm for the outdoor demo.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;The crowd seems to have maybe shrunk a little compared to a couple of hours ago,&quot; police told Yle on Sunday afternoon, when it seemed like around 30-40 people were in attendance.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">They also said that Saturday&#39;s protest had been small during the day, but gathered bigger crowds towards the evening.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 17:43:47 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>COVID-19</category><category>kotimaa</category><category>politiikka</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12304724</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91109861ff597a800bf.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Finland unveils plan for electric aircraft routes across Lapland region</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12302109?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The trial period will initially begin with the use of renewable aviation fuel, but will later switch to using electric aircraft.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">An experimental project operating out of Enontekiö Airport in the northwest corner of Finland is set to test the viability of using electric airplanes to fly routes across the wider Lapland region.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;When someone from Enontekiö leaves for Rovaniemi, the journey takes at least four hours by car, but flying would take half an hour,&quot; Enontekiö Airport CEO <strong class="yle__article__strong">Marko Halla</strong> told Yle.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The advent of electric planes has the potential to revolutionise travel, as routes could become more profitable even with smaller numbers of passengers.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">That could mean the beginning of year-round air traffic at Enontekiö Airport, Halla predicted.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Lapland&#39;s internal air traffic is designed so that it can be operated by electric aircraft. The location of Enontekiö is central, the longest flight distance from here is about 300 kilometres, and the range of an electric plane is good enough for that,&quot; he said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">A route from Rovaniemi to Tromsø in Norway, via Enontekiö, will be trialled during the autumn. The journey takes about eight hours by car, but only one hour by plane - including stopovers. Initially, a 19-seater propeller turbine aircraft will fly the route.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;There are a lot of Finnish workers in northern Norway, as the University of Tromsø cooperates with Finnish universities, so students, researchers and professors travel there. And an important group are tourists, there is a lot of tourist traffic between Rovaniemi and Tromsø,&quot; Halla said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">He added that the reform of Finland&#39;s social and healthcare services could lead to an increased need to travel, in particular if specialised care becomes centralised in one part of the region, and reduced travel times may benefit patients. A patient could be transferred from Ivalo to Rovaniemi within one hour by plane, he pointed out, a journey that would take between three and four hours by road.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Renewable fuels to help cut aviation emissions</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Initially, the new routes to and from Enontekiö will be flown by aircraft with internal combustion engines using renewable aviation fuel.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Authorities in both Sweden and Norway have previously announced that domestic flights will be fossil-free within a decade. Finland has not yet made any such commitment.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">However, electric aircrafts are just one option for reducing aviation emissions in the future.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Airlines have a lot of internal combustion engine equipment, and solutions must be found that can be used in an economical and at the same time in an environmentally responsible way,&quot; according to <strong class="yle__article__strong">Henri Hansson</strong>, Technical Director of the airport company Finavia.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><em class="yle__article__emphasis">Story continues after photo</em></p>
<figure class="yle__article__figure"><img class="yle__article__figure__image" width=958 height=639 src="//images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload/w_958,h_639/39-90994461faf17ac311e.jpg" alt="Lentokoneenvalmistaja ATR on testannut pelkän uusiutuvan lentopolttoaineen käyttöä ATR 72-600 -konetyypissä"><figcaption class="yle__article__figure__caption"><span class="yle__article__figure__caption__text">100% renewable aviation fuel produced by Neste has been tested in the ATR 72-600 propeller turbine aircraft.</span><span class="yle__article__figure__caption__source">ATR</span></figcaption></figure>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The short-term solution for the next few years will be using renewable aviation fuels, the use of which will increase as production increases. Hansson added that existing internal combustion engines can also be converted to use hydrogen and hydrogen-based electric fuels.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Existing internal combustion engines will be used in aviation for a long time, using renewable aviation fuel. Electric flights are a new option for the short-term, and the hydrogen economy for longer-term, enabling airlines to produce efficient long-haul routes,&quot; Hansson said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The EU set a net zero target for CO2 emissions from international aviation by 2050 at the Glasgow climate summit last year. This will require a significant increase in the use of renewable aviation fuels, among other objectives.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 16:55:00 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>matkailu</category><category>ilmasto</category><category>ilmastonmuutos</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12302109</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/13-3-12300481.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Niskanen takes bronze in Olympic Skiathlon</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12304463?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Finnish skier Iivo Niskanen finished behind two Russians.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Finland&#39;s first medal of the <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12298038">Beijing Winter Olympics</a> came on Sunday, when skier <strong class="yle__article__strong">Iivo Niskanen</strong> took the bronze in the 15km + 15km Skiathlon event.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Niskanen finished behind <strong class="yle__article__strong">Alexander Bolshunov</strong> and <strong class="yle__article__strong">Denis Spitsov</strong>, who were competing under the flag of the Russian Olympic Committee.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I just couldn&#39;t keep pace with those Russians,&quot; said Niskanen after the race. &quot;They were just ridiculously fast today. Unbelievable, the speed they can cki at. It was even a little bit surprising that I wasn&#39;t able to respond to them at all.&quot;</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">It is Niskanen&#39;s third Olympic medal, having taken gold in the team sprint in the 2014 Sochi games and gold in the 50km individual race in Pyeongchang in 2018.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><strong class="yle__article__strong">Perttu Hyvärinen</strong> finished seventh in the competition, while <strong class="yle__article__strong">Remi Lindholm</strong> was 25th in his debut Olympics.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><em class="yle__article__emphasis">This week&#39;s All Points North looked at the prospects of Finnish medals in Beijing. You can listen to the full podcast using the embedded player here, via</em> <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://areena.yle.fi/audio/1-4355773">Yle Areena</a><em class="yle__article__emphasis">,</em> <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://open.spotify.com/show/11M4NJ3cfmNCo0qYiIXXU1">Spotify</a><em class="yle__article__emphasis">,</em> <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://podcasts.apple.com/fi/podcast/all-points-north/id1347167993">Apple Podcasts</a> <em class="yle__article__emphasis">or on your usual podcast player using the RSS feed.</em></p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><em class="yle__article__emphasis">Article continues after audio.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 10:54:55 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>urheilu</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12304463</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91111761ff87c2255b1.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Finland hockey coach slams 'human rights violation' of China quarantine rules</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12304429?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Finland's captain has been in quarantine since he arrived in China.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">China is violating the human rights of a Finnish ice hockey player by keeping him in quarantine after testing positive for coronavirus, according to the team&#39;s coach <strong class="yle__article__strong">Jukka Jalonen</strong>.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><strong class="yle__article__strong">Marko Anttila</strong> has been asymptomatic since he tested positive on 18 January, and subsequently recorded a test result that allowed him to travel to China for the Beijing Olympics. In China, however, he tested positive again and was sent to a quarantine hotel, where he has remained.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;This violates human rights,&quot; said Lions&#39; coach Jukka Jalonen at a press conference on Sunday. &quot;An elite athlete who is completely healthy cannot compete in the Olympics. In Finland there are apparently more lottery millionaires than Olympic athletes, so it&#39;s not every boy or girl that gets to go to the dance.&quot;</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Finland start their Olympic campaign on 10 February against Slovakia. Jalonen said Anttila is doing as well as can be expected in the circumstances.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I spoke to him yesterday,&quot; said Jalonen. &quot;Marko is a strong guy, mentally. He is not depressed, but he&#39;s pretty down. A couple of times a day he gets cold and tasteless spaghetti bolognese.&quot;</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">To get out of quarantine, Anttila has to provide samples meeting the Chinese authorities&#39; stipulations three days in a row.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">If Anttila records a CT value above 35 three days in a row, he will be allowed to leave quarantine. The CT value indicates how much virus a person is carrying, and if the value is 35 or above the risk of onward infection is regarded as very low.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The number is based on the number of &#39;cycles of amplification&#39; a PCR test needs to identify a coronavirus infection. The more cycles required, the less Covid is present.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Team doctor <strong class="yle__article__strong">Maarit Valtonen</strong> said that Anttila&#39;s results are a borderline case, and she has discussed with her counterparts from other countries how the situation could be resolved to get Anttila and others in his situation out of isolation.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;The so-called long tail can show in tests for a long time [after infection] and with big CT values some lab could declare it positive or completely negative,&quot; said Valtonen on 24 January.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Anttila plays for Helsinki club Jokerit, which is part-owned by Norilsk Nickel, in the Kontinental Hockey League, a Russian-owned organisation that includes teams from Belarus, China, Kazakhstan, Finland and Latvia.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 10:07:55 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>urheilu</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12304429</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-89585761c3635305b34.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Convoy protesters threatened, harassed journalists at Friday's demo</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12304211?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Reporters say they faced hostility from protesters.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Reporters covering the Convoy Finland 2022 protests in central Helsinki on Friday evening say they faced verbal and physical harassment as they went about their jobs.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Yle&#39;s reporter and cameraperson on the scene say they were continually threatened verbally and physically. Some protesters attempted to prevent reporters from moving around freely.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Journalists were abused and threatened, and one protester attempted to steal a bag containing the camera operator&#39;s equipment.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Protesters also tried to steal the reporter&#39;s microphone. Iltalehti duty editor Niina Huuhtanen said that her paper&#39;s reporters also faced continual harassment, with threats and abuse directed towards them.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The IL reporter was shoved and a microphone was taken, and there was an attempt to steal their camera.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">MTV also reported similar incidents, with police removing one person before they started their live stream. In addition several people approached the MTV reporter to film their face.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">MTV&#39;s duty editor <strong class="yle__article__strong">Päivi Hannula</strong> said that the reporter had covered many demos before, but had never previously seen similar behaviour directed at the media.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Ilta-Sanomat&#39;s reporters said they experienced nothing worse than drunken shouting, with no threats or physical intimidation.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Yle did not reach Helsingin Sanomat to ask for their reporters&#39; experiences.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police broke up the convoy protest after midnight, when protesters refused to disperse. They <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12303909">detained 55 people</a>, including two for obstructing police, and said that one of their trucks (used to tow vehicles parked to block the road) had its tyre slashed.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police have advised the general public to be prepared for disrupted traffic in central Helsinki on Saturday, as the demonstrations enter a second day.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 17:30:16 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>Helsinki</category><category>rikokset</category><category>yhteiskunta</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12304211</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91087861fd9a0c8af40.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Runeberg Prize goes to Quynh Tran for debut novel</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12304155?origin=rss</link>
          <description></description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">This year&#39;s Runeberg prize was given to <strong class="yle__article__strong">Quynh Tran</strong>, an author from Jakobstad, for his work Skugga och svalka (English translation <em class="yle__article__emphasis">Shadow and Coolness</em>).</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The book reflects his own background, telling the story of a Vietnamese family in a coastal Ostrobothnian town. Tran himself grew up in Jakobstad, where his family moved from Vietnam in 1989.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Tran&#39;s novel does not accuse or offer ready explanations, but gives the reader a chance to interpret for themselves. The distinctively-voiced novel is a refreshing addition to Finnish literature, a varied and beautiful package.&quot;</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">32-year-old Tran said he was shocked to get this recognition for his very first work.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I don&#39;t quite believe it yet,&quot; he told Yle. &quot;The prize is a really big surprise. I have only just gotten used to the idea that people read a book that I&#39;ve written.&quot;</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The prize is worth 20,000 euros and is awarded by the Uusimaa newspaper, the city of Porvoo, the Union of Finnish writers, the the Finnish Critics&#39; Association and the Society of Swedish Authors in Finland.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The first prize was given in 1986 and is handed out on Runeberg Day, the annual celebration of <strong class="yle__article__strong">Johan Ludvig Runeberg</strong>, one of the national poets of Finland who also has a cake named in his honour.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 16:40:10 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>kotimaa</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12304155</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-873784617c45a818a85.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Appeals court fines Finn Spring water firm for environmental damage</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12303645?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The companies' plants had reportedly discharged inadequately treated wastewater into the environment for several years. </description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The Vaasa Court of Appeal has ordered two food manufacturing firms to pay several thousands of euros worth of penalties for causing environmental damage in Central Ostrobothnia.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Finnish spring water manufacturing giant Finn Spring and protein bar manufacturer Leader Snack have been charged with releasing inadequately treated wastewater at their plants for several years, subsequently violating the conditions of their environmental permit and polluting the surrounding area.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Finn Spring was made to pay 40,000 euros in corporate fines and 250,000 euros to the state for damages caused at its factories in Toholampi and Lestijärvi.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Leader Snack will have to shell out 15,000 euros in corporate fines and 50,000 euros to the state for pollution at its Toholampi plant, located in the same yard as Finn Spring&#39;s.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">While the district court dismissed the case and acquitted the companies of all charges about a year ago, the prosecutor and the Centres for Economic Development, Transport and the Environment appealed that verdict.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Company bosses charged </h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Finn Spring&#39;s CEO and administrative director have also been sentenced to pay income-linked day fines for environmental damage.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The CEO received a 60-day fine, equivalent to 8,100 euros, while the administrative director will have to pay a 40-day fine amounting to 4,880 euros.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The CEO of Leader Snack was also charged with a 40-day fine equivalent to 2,280 euros.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The court found that the company heads had neglected their duty to ensure that the wastewater was treated properly and would not cause any issues upon being released into surrounding ditches and water bodies.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The executives also failed to take the environmental impact of the plants&#39; activities into account, the court said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to the findings, there was a clear link between the plants&#39; discharge pipes and the growth of sewage fungus in Lestijärvi and Toholampi in the past few years. The primary cause of the fungal growth, which caused significant pollution, was found to be excessive sugar in the wastewater.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The appeals court ruled that Finn Spring&#39;s conduct on the whole had been grossly negligent, as the company was required to monitor sugar levels in its wastewater, which had already exceeded permissible amounts on multiple occasions between 2005 and 2019.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Based on the findings, the water manufacturer did not possess an appropriate wastewater management plan or an adequate understanding of the risks of releasing water containing sugar into the environment.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The accused in the district court case included Finn Spring and the swimming pool it runs, Lylyn Pisara, Leader Snack and beverage manufacturer Bullberry. Bullberry, which has since gone bankrupt, has not yet received a sentence.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The prosecutor had demanded Finn Spring pay a total of 650,00 euros and Leader Snack pay a total of 210,000 euros in penalties during the first case.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 13:15:31 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>kotimaa</category><category>luonto</category><category>rikokset</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12303645</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/13-3-10854239.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>EVA: More women bosses than ever before</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12302263?origin=rss</link>
          <description>A survey suggests female managers are now more common than ever.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Women&#39;s share of jobs managing companies, agencies and NGOs has risen higher than ever before, according to the business-backed think tank EVA.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The think tanks &#39;glass ceiling index&#39; suggests that some 37.5 percent of managers in Finland were women in 2020. That&#39;s up from 36.8 percent the year before.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The figure has risen considerably in recent years, with the index recording 31.4 percent women leaders in 2017. EVA says Finland has more women in leadership positions than the average OECD country, with the OECD average at 33.6 percent in 2020.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Finland remains behind Sweden and the United States, where women take more than 40 percent of leadership positions, but is clearly ahead of Germany.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>talous</category><category>yhteiskunta</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12302263</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-90985661fa9a9a52d5c.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Police break up Convoy Finland protest, detain 55</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12303909?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The protesters say they want cheaper petrol and an end to coronavirus restrictions.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police detained some 55 protesters outside parliament when they broke up a &#39;convoy&#39; demonstration that had blocked traffic for several hours in pursuit of demands including cheaper petrol and the resignation of the government.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police began towing vehicles parked on Mannerheimintie when the protesters did not disperse when instructed to do so just after midnight.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Two of the detainees were taken in on suspicion of obstructing an official carrying out his duties, and police tweeted that one of their tow trucks had its tyres punctured with a sharp implement.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The group&#39;s demands included the removal of all covid-related restrictions, even though the government has announced it aims to remove them by the middle of this month.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">They have said they will continue their protest on Saturday at Citizen&#39;s Square, opposite the parliament building.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 09:43:36 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>politiikka</category><category>yhteiskunta</category><category>terveys</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12303909</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91086761fd9363a4f05.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Union: UPM strike to continue into March</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12302948?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The strike has lasted for five weeks and could go on for three more.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The Paperworker&#39;s Union announced on Friday that UPM plant workers will continue their strike till 12 March if they do not reach a deal with the company over a new collective agreement before then.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The strike began on 1 January, 2022. The union has been in negotiations with UPM regarding the details of the agreement, which determines pay and conditions in the paper industry.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Following a <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12281536">ruling</a> from the District Court of Helsinki in January, UPM employees in certain power and water treatment plants were compelled to return to work to prevent the strike from affecting critical services such as district heating.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Paper union ready to negotiate</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Traditionally, Finnish labour talks have been sector-wide, with a collective agreement guaranteeing industrial peace between unions and companies.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Representatives from UPM said they would prefer to negotiate unit-by-unit in this instance, as managers claim the businesses differ from each other so vastly that a single collective agreement would not be applicable.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Following a meeting, the Paperworker&#39;s Union also announced on Friday that it is willing to negotiate on a unit-by-unit basis with UPM.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The union has already entered into company-specific agreements with other forest industry giants Stora Enso and Metsä Group.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 16:12:12 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>kotimaa</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12302948</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-90969361fa80ae66b85.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Lindén becomes social services minister, Kiuru begins maternity leave</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12302591?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Aki Lindén is serving his first term as an MP following a long career in healthcare administration, including as CEO of the Helsinki and Uusimaa Hospital District (HUS).</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Social Democratic Party MP <strong class="yle__article__strong">Aki Lindén</strong> has been confirmed as Minister of Family Affairs and Social Services, replacing his party colleague <strong class="yle__article__strong">Krista Kiuru</strong>, who begins her maternity leave on Friday.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The 69-year-old Lindén is serving his first term as an MP following a long career in healthcare administration, including roles as Director of Health Care in the west coast city of Pori, Director of the Hospital District of Southwest Finland and CEO of the Helsinki and Uusimaa Hospital District (HUS).</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">His experience and expertise in the healthcare sector has earned the respect of party colleagues, and he is expected to take an even tougher line than his predecessor on health matters.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Lindén has been a staunch supporter of tight restrictions throughout the Covid pandemic as a means of alleviating the burden on healthcare services.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">As well as becoming social services minister, he will also chair the government’s coronavirus ministerial working group, where his views on handling the pandemic will have important sway.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">At a press conference on Friday confirming his nomination as minister, Lindén said he was in favour of a gradual easing of Covid restrictions.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I&#39;m interested in the scale here. If there are at least 600 coronavirus patients in hospitals, then certain restrictions should apply. If there are half of the patients, or 300, the restrictions would be something else and if fewer, then maybe not at all,&quot; he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 15:16:14 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>politiikka</category><category>terveys</category><category>COVID-19</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12302591</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-5904455d79e315cbccc.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Survey: two thirds trust Finland's ability to defend against a military attack</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12302417?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Less than half feel that Finland will be able to protect Åland, where military presence is prohibited.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">According to a survey by agrarian newspaper Maaseudun Tulevaisuus, two thirds of people in Finland believe that the country possesses the military capability required to adequately defend itself from an attack.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Every fourth respondent said they have doubts about Finland&#39;s defence abilities.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Ongoing tensions have led to increasingly strained relations between Russia and western countries and prompted fears of renewed conflict in the region.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The survey found significant disparities in city dwellers and rural communities in terms of trust in the military. While the former appear to be more sceptical in general, rural residents are more likely to believe in the country&#39;s ability to defend itself.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Trust in Finland&#39;s military capability is lowest in the Helsinki metropolitan area, with one in three respondents saying they do not believe defence forces could protect the entire country in case of an attack.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Age also appears to be an influencing factor. The survey found that those under the age of 30 and over the age of 64 believe that Finland can adequately defend itself, while middle-aged individuals have less faith in the country&#39;s military prowess.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The survey also included specific questions related to the autonomous island region Åland.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><em class="yle__article__emphasis">Story continues after photo.</em></p>
<figure class="yle__article__figure"><img class="yle__article__figure__image" width=960 height=640 src="//images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload/w_960,h_640/39-91022561fbd3cc51e53.jpg" alt="Kastelholman linna Ahvenanmaalla."><figcaption class="yle__article__figure__caption"><span class="yle__article__figure__caption__text">The Kastelholm Castle in Åland was once used for defense purposes. The region is now demilitarised.</span><span class="yle__article__figure__caption__source">Tuomas Lehtinen / AOP</span></figcaption></figure>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Just under half of respondents said they believe that Finland would be able to protect the province fairly well. About one in 10 think Åland would be vulnerable to an attack.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The Swedish-speaking island region is autonomous, neutral and demilitarised, which means that any kind of military presence and fortification is strictly forbidden. However, historic treaties obligate Finland to protect the islands in case of a security threat.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Åland was recently the subject of a security debate due to its strategically important location following the appearance of Russian warships in the Baltic Sea.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The survey, which was conducted within the past two weeks, included 1,030 respondents residing in Finland. The sample did not include anyone from Åland.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 14:00:25 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>ulkopolitiikka</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12302417</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-90777261f3bcf68adff.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Convoy protest set to disrupt traffic in Helsinki</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12302166?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Police are predicting traffic problems as a result of the protest.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The Convoy Finland protest starts on Friday in Helsinki, with demonstrators saying they plan to gather from 6pm until 10pm in protest at Covid restrictions and high fuel costs.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The protest will continue on Saturday from 10am until 10pm, according to organisers.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The protesters&#39; demands include the end of all Covid-related restrictions in Finland, a 50 percent reduction in fuel taxes, and the resignation of the current government.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Organisers have told police that they plan to use civil disobedience tactics to press their claims. Police say they believe the aim is to block off traffic into and out of central Helsinki.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Police ban heavy goods vehicles from the centre </h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police have allocated additional resources to police the protest, and brought in a ban on heavy goods vehicles in the city centre. Vehicles over 12 metres long will require a special permit to enter the area where restrictions are in force at the centre of the capital.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police have urged those who want to express their opinion to do so at Citizens Square opposite parliament.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Traffic disruption could last a while </h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police have not yet offered an estimate on how many participants are likely to attend, but say the event could cause significant and long-lasting traffic disruption.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The Convoy Finland 2022 group on Facebook has some 63,000 members.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Police are recommending motorists avoid the city centre from Friday evening until the protest has ended, and say they will offer updates in real-time via their <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://twitter.com/HelsinkiPoliisi">Twitter account. </a></p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Helsinki Region Transport (HSL) warned on Thursday that the demonstration could cause delays to public transport in central Helsinki on Friday evening. Disruption could affect trams and buses, with some diversions expected to be in operation.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">HSL warned travellers to allow extra time for their journeys.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 11:49:10 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>COVID-19</category><category>liikenne</category><category>politiikka</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12302166</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-90810261f40b5d6df43.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Appeal Court quashes Aarnio murder conviction</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12302025?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The district court had previously sentenced the former head of Helsinki police department’s narcotics unit to life imprisonment for his role in the 2003 murder.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The Helsinki Court of Appeal has overturned the guilty verdict handed down to <strong class="yle__article__strong">Jari Aarnio</strong> for his role in a 2003 murder.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Helsinki District Court <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-11711933">previously ruled</a> that Aarnio had advance knowledge of the <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-10745733">planned contract killing</a> of Swedish-Turkish national <strong class="yle__article__strong">Volgan Ünsal</strong> but did nothing to prevent the crime from taking place.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The court sentenced Aarnio, the former head of Helsinki police department’s narcotics unit, to life imprisonment.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">However, the appeal court found that Aarnio had no special responsibility to prevent the murder and did not appear to have contributed to the act, and also rejected the prosecutor&#39;s alternative charge that Aarnio be convicted of aiding and abetting murder.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The court further upheld the lower court&#39;s decision to dismiss the murder charge against Aarnio’s co-accused, former gang boss <strong class="yle__article__strong">Keijo Vilhunen</strong>. The District Court had previously ruled that the prosecution had not proved beyond a reasonable doubt that Vilhunen had been involved.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Advance knowledge of murder</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">During the district court case, the prosecutor said that Aarnio was informed in the summer of 2003 that a contract had been taken out on the life of Ünsal, who had stolen money from an accomplice following a robbery at Stockholm’s Arlanda Airport.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Ünsal went into a witness protection programme, but subsequently left it.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Aarnio warned Swedish police of the murder plot sometime before Ünsal travelled to Finland in September 2003, which the district court found to mean Aarnio had a duty of responsibility to protect the life of Ünsal, as he also imposed surveillance on the suspected perpetrators within Finland. However, he failed to tell others of his advance knowledge and did not take any action to protect Ünsal.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Four men – three Finnish nationals and a Swedish man who ordered the hit – were sentenced to life imprisonment for the murder, which took place on 16 October 2003 in Vuosaari, Helsinki.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Aarnio is already <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/uutiset/osasto/news/corrupt_ex-police_chief_jari_aarnio_begins_13_year_sentence_as_court_upholds_guilty_verdict/10850501">serving a 13-year prison sentence</a> for a slew of offences related to drug trafficking and official misconduct.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 10:55:12 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>rikokset</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12302025</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-7160255f55e3e529a20.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Olkiluoto 3 electricity production hit by further delay</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12301825?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The OL3 nuclear reactor is expected to produce around 14 percent of Finland’s electricity once it begins operating at full capacity.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Electricity production at the new Olkiluoto 3 nuclear reactor in southwest Finland has been hit by yet further delays.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Production had been <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12258950">set to begin</a> in January, but this was <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12289183">postponed</a> until early February.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In a press release, the facility&#39;s operator Teollisuuden Voima (TVO) said the much-delayed reactor will instead begin producing electricity at the end of February.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;During the OL3 plant unit’s test production phase, it was observed that there is a need for modifications in the plant unit’s automation related to control functions, as well as further testing related to the modifications,&quot; the statement said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The delay also means that regular electricity production will begin in July, and not June as planned. Production will operate at 30 percent capacity until then.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The OL3 reactor was originally intended to start generating electricity in 2009, but the project has been hit by a catalogue of delays, including <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/uutiset/osasto/news/olkiluoto_3_reactor_delayed_yet_again_now_12_years_behind_schedule/11128489">faulty components</a> and <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/uutiset/osasto/news/long-delayed_olkiluoto_3_nuclear_reactor_to_go_online_in_january_2020/10532547">safety tests</a>, even leading to <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/uutiset/osasto/news/tvo_steps_up_legal_battle_over_olkiluoto_3_reactor_delays/9196907">lawsuits</a> between TVO and the French firm Areva.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The OL3 reactor is expected to produce around 14 percent of Finland’s electricity once it is fully operational.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 10:14:39 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>energia</category><category>kotimaa</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12301825</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-884214619fa81945f58.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Friday's papers: EU guarantees, Nokia success and Mustonen's return</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12301839?origin=rss</link>
          <description>EU President Ursula von der Leyen visited Helsinki on Thursday.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Security policy has been in the news recently, with actors including the US, Russia and Nato discussing the security situation with Finland.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">On Thursday it was the turn of the European Union, as EU Commission President <strong class="yle__article__strong">Ursula von der Leyen</strong> came to Helsinki to meet Prime Minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Sanna Marin</strong> (SDP) and President <strong class="yle__article__strong">Sauli Niinistö</strong>.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In her comments to the press she even raised the EU&#39;s common security clause, Article 42.7, which states that EU countries must provide help if a member state is under attack.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The clause does not specify that the help must be military in nature, but it is often cited as an indication that Finland is no longer properly &#39;neutral&#39;. In its report on von der Leyen&#39;s visit, Helsingin Sanomat <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.hs.fi/paivanlehti/04022022/art-2000008583270.html">reminds</a> readers that Niinistö has frequently asked what help exactly would be offered.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">In the context of Finland&#39;s ongoing debate about whether or not to join Nato, and Russia&#39;s demands that Nato not expand further, the devil is in the details.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Niinistö has said he&#39;s been disappointed about the attention Russia&#39;s demands have received since the letters were sent earlier this week.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Nokia doing well</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">It&#39;s end-of-year results season in the corporate world, and business daily Kauppalehti is <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.kauppalehti.fi/uutiset/nokian-menestys-on-koko-suomen-asia/8fbf19ed-2911-4e9e-b6c8-773fb03700e6">singing the praises</a> of an old Finnish favourite: Nokia.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The company returned to profitability and proposed a dividend of 0.08 euros a share, which is great news for the many Finns who — still — hold Nokia shares.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The results indicated that the company has finally gotten past the absorption of French firm Alcatel-Lucent, which was acquired in 2016.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">KL suggests that geopolitical concerns might be a boost for Nokia, with Chinese competitor Huawei viewed with suspicion in many European capitals.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">As 5g and faster networks roll out across the globe, KL says companies like Nokia become more important — and that can only be good for Finland.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Mustonen goes home</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Most papers are <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://www.iltalehti.fi/pekingin-olympialaiset-2022/a/16465606-5c6a-491e-8f00-cafd0cd37c19">reporting</a> on hockey coach <strong class="yle__article__strong">Pasi Mustonen&#39;s</strong> decision to leave Beijing to return to Finland after only one game of the women&#39;s national team&#39;s tournament, which they lost 5-2 to the United States.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Mustonen said his decision was down to a serious illness in his family, and declined to take any questions from the media.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The team will now be led by assistant coach <strong class="yle__article__strong">Jussi Toivola</strong>, who is slated to take over from Mustonen after the Olympics anyway.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 09:30:03 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>politiikka</category><category>Suomen politiikka</category><category>Nato</category><category>ulkopolitiikka</category><category>Suomen ulkopolitiikka</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12301839</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91020561fbd014420d3.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>EU coordinating response to Russian letter, says von der Leyen in Helsinki</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12300502?origin=rss</link>
          <description>The EU President said that Finland can count on European solidarity.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">European Commission President <strong class="yle__article__strong">Ursula von der Leyen</strong> held talks in Helsinki on Friday with Prime Minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Sanna Marin</strong> (SDP).</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The two met at the prime minister&#39;s residence to discuss issues including the security situation in Europe. Speaking briefly to reporters outside afterwards, they stressed the importance of maintaining a dialogue amid rising tensions over Ukraine.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;First and foremost Russia needs to de-escalate,&quot; Marin said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Von der Leyen confirmed that the EU is coordinating a response to letters sent by Russian Foreign Minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Sergei Lavrov</strong> this week. In the letters, Russia reiterated its previous security demands.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">On Wednesday, Swedish Foreign Minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Ann Linde</strong> said that her country would co-ordinate its response with Finland. The two countries are among a half-dozen EU states that are not members of Nato.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Lavrov&#39;s letter stipulates that it expects direct answers from each country “and not within any bloc or in the name thereof&quot;.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Von der Leyen said that Finland can count on EU solidarity, adding that the challenge posed by Russia to European security concerns all EU countries.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">2 presidents meet, unlike last visit</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Unlike on von der Leyen&#39;s <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12126461">last visit in October</a>, this time she also met with President <strong class="yle__article__strong">Sauli Niinistö</strong>.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Many key figures have recently been in contact with Niinistö, one of few western leaders to maintain a close dialogue with Russian President <strong class="yle__article__strong">Vladimir Putin</strong>, mostly recently in a phone call on 21 January.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Under the Finnish constitution, EU affairs are handled by the cabinet while the president oversees general foreign policy.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 16:12:29 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>ulkopolitiikka</category><category>Venäjä</category><category>Euroopan unioni</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12300502</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91020561fbd014420d3.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>APN podcast: Is Finland on track for Olympic success?</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12300654?origin=rss</link>
          <description>All Points North previews Finland's prospects at the Winter Olympics, follows up on a story about the exploitation of foreign workers, and tags along for an icy adventure.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">This week All Points North assesses the chances of Finnish athletes at the Beijing Winter Olympics, as Finland aims to maintain its proud record of winning medals at every edition of the games since the very first in 1924.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Preparations for the games have been overshadowed by the Covid pandemic as well as a <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12298948">diplomatic boycott</a>, but <strong class="yle__article__strong">Ilkka Palomäki</strong> of the Finnish Olympic Committee told APN that the focus should now switch to the skiers, skaters and snowboarders vying for Olympic glory.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;The athletes are here to compete — for most of them this is the biggest competition of their lives and I think everybody should respect that,&quot; Palomäki said.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><em class="yle__article__emphasis">You can listen to the full podcast using the embedded player here, via</em> <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://areena.yle.fi/audio/1-4355773">Yle Areena</a><em class="yle__article__emphasis">,</em> <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://open.spotify.com/show/11M4NJ3cfmNCo0qYiIXXU1">Spotify</a><em class="yle__article__emphasis">,</em> <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://podcasts.apple.com/fi/podcast/all-points-north/id1347167993">Apple Podcasts</a> <em class="yle__article__emphasis">or on your usual podcast player using the RSS feed.</em></p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><em class="yle__article__emphasis">Article continues after audio.</em></p>

<p class="yle__article__paragraph">APN also follows up on a <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12263317">recent story</a> about the exploitation of foreign workers in Finland, when Yle&#39;s MOT investigative journalism unit uncovered poor working conditions and hygiene standards at a central kitchen operated by the coffeehouse chain Espresso House.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">One former employee of the kitchen, <strong class="yle__article__strong">Ana-Maria Albastroiu</strong>, told APN that the responsibility should be on employers to proactively identify and stamp out any exploitative practices, rather than waiting for workers to report them.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;We should also highlight companies who take advantage of workers because yes, workers should know their rights, but companies taking advantage of workers not knowing their rights is a big problem. How can we stop that? How can we actually hold companies accountable,&quot; she said.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">"Have a friend"</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">This week we also sent our roving reporter <strong class="yle__article__strong">Melanie Hall</strong> out onto the frozen Tuusulanjärvi lake in southern Finland to learn more about the importance of measuring ice thickness.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">There are multiple reports every year of people falling through weak ice and drowning, with last year seeing the <a class="yle__article__link" href="https://yle.fi/news/3-12262868">highest number of drowning deaths</a> in Finland for over a decade.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph"><strong class="yle__article__strong">Antti Niemi</strong> and <strong class="yle__article__strong">Veli Sipola</strong>, collectively known as the <em class="yle__article__emphasis">Jäähavaintomiehet</em> (roughly translated as &#39;ice observation men&#39;), told APN that there are many preventative measures people can take when stepping out onto the frozen lake, including always bringing a friend along.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;Never go alone if you don&#39;t know the environment,&quot; Niemi advised.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Join the conversation!</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">This week&#39;s show was presented by <strong class="yle__article__strong">Ronan Browne</strong> and <strong class="yle__article__strong">Egan Richardson</strong> and featured a segment from <strong class="yle__article__strong">Melanie Hall</strong>. It was produced by <strong class="yle__article__strong">Mark B. Odom</strong> and the audio engineer was <strong class="yle__article__strong">Laura Koso</strong>.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">If you have any questions or would like to share your thoughts, contact us via WhatsApp on +358 44 421 0909, on our Facebook or Twitter accounts, or at yle.news@yle.fi and allpointsnorth@yle.fi.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 15:31:26 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>urheilu</category><category>All Points North</category><category>työelämä</category><category>kotimaa</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12300654</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91020961fbd0aee7628.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Cultural sector protests Covid restrictions, minister 'understands' frustration</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12300541?origin=rss</link>
          <description>Cultural figures called for more financial compensation and a programme to help the sector recover from the crisis.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Figures from the culture and event sectors gathered in central Helsinki on Thursday to protest against restrictions on mass events brought in to prevent superspreading events during the Covid pandemic.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Using the slogan &quot;the Final Lockdown&quot;, an estimated 2,000 protesters demanded that the current measures in place be the last, and that no further restrictions be brought in.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">They also called for more financial compensation and a programme to help the sector recover from the crisis. Similar events were held in other cities.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Pop-rock singer <strong class="yle__article__strong">Anssi Kela</strong> said that the music business had been in a &#39;completely absurd&#39; situation for two years since the start of the epidemic in Finland.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Kela, who has multiple hit records during his long career, said that big names were necessary to draw attention to the industry&#39;s problems.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;People may easily think that successful artists are complaining about not getting paid,&quot; said Kela. &quot;But it took a really long time before this large sector&#39;s distress was even noticed.&quot;</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The sector has been under restrictions of some sort since March 2020. A concert on International Women&#39;s Day, 8 March, was suspected to have exposed 100 people to coronavirus, after the city of Helsinki announced seven people had contracted the virus after attending it.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Eight days after that concert, Finland declared a state of emergency and closed down large parts of society, including cultural venues.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Culture Minister <strong class="yle__article__strong">Antti Kurvinen</strong> (Cen) said on Thursday that he understood the sector&#39;s annoyance.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">&quot;I understand why this protest has been called,&quot; said Kurvinen. &quot;These people&#39;s message and demands are certainly fully justified.&quot;</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">He said that the situation was now set to ease, with restrictions to be lifted from mid-February. Although protest organisers did not give him time to speak on stage, he also told the media that the next pandemic would be better as the government is planning to bring in a general benefit for those whose livelihoods are affected by restrictions.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 14:06:18 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>kulttuuri</category><category>COVID-19</category><category>terveys</category><category>yhteiskunta</category><category>kotimaa</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12300541</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-91012061fbb09105d66.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item><item>
          <title>Omicron spread levels off, clear drop in ICU load</title>
          <link>https://yle.fi/news/3-12300025?origin=rss</link>
          <description>While daily death figures remain high, health officials point to hopeful signs that the Omicron surge is waning.</description>
          <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Health authorities pointed to signs of improvement in the coronavirus situation at their weekly coronavirus briefing on Thursday. The number of patients in intensive care has dropped by one third in the past week.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Officials from the Ministry of Social Affairs and Health (MSAH) and the Finnish Institute for Health and Welfare (THL) said that the Omicron wave, which began about two months ago, has plateaued nationally. However, there are still significant regional differences, they said. In some areas, the pandemic may have peaked, while in others the situation is largely unchanged and could still worsen.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Infection pressures on the population remain high, but the consequences of infections in relation to their number are clearly milder than in previous waves, officials said at the press conference in Helsinki.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The most significant risks are now for the ever-decreasing number of unvaccinated people and those who, for one reason or another, do not have adequate protection against the serious consequences of the illness.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">ICU load lightens</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The need for intensive care due to Covid-19 is clearly declining.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">There were 32 patients in intensive care units on Thursday, compared to 49 a week earlier, a decline of about one-third.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">A significant proportion of Covid-infected patients are primarily in hospital for some other reason, an estimated one in four patients in regular wards and one in five in intensive care units, said Professor <strong class="yle__article__strong">Matti Reinikainen</strong> of Kuopio University Hospital at the briefing.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">From Wednesday to Thursday, 6,788 new coronavirus infections were confirmed at labs, the THL said. Twenty-nine more deaths were reported.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Two-thirds of ICU patients male</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">A total of 250 coronavirus-related deaths have been reported in the last two weeks. Eighty-two percent of these patients were over 70 years old and an average age of 82.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">During the two-year pandemic, nearly 1,600 Covid-positive individuals have been treated in intensive care. Two-thirds of these have been male, with a median age of 57 years. The average duration of intensive care has been 11 days.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">The mortality rate rises after the age of 60. About one in four people aged 60-69 have died despite intensive care. About half of those over the age of 80 have died despite treatment.</p>
<h3 class="yle__article__heading yle__article__heading--h3">Vaccinations up, RNA in waste water down</h3>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">More than 90 percent of those aged 60 and over who have received two doses of the vaccine have also received a third dose, said <strong class="yle__article__strong">Anna Katz</strong>, project manager at THL.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Katz points out that the protection afforded by the second vaccination expires after about six months.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Meanwhile the rise in levels of coronavirus residues in wastewater has been reversed in most areas, which the ministry&#39;s Director of Strategic Affairs, <strong class="yle__article__strong">Liisa-Maria Voipio-Pulkki</strong>, called &quot;a positive sign&quot;.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">However the upward trend seems to be still continuing in Oulu and has only slowed slightly in Tampere, Jyväskylä and Pori.</p>
<p class="yle__article__paragraph">Coronavirus RNA can still be excreted in wastewater for an average of three weeks after infection.</p>]]></content:encoded>
          <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 12:22:43 +0200</pubDate>
          <category>COVID-19</category><category>terveys</category>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">https://yle.fi/news/3-12300025</guid>
          <enclosure url="https://images.cdn.yle.fi/image/upload//w_205,h_115,q_70/39-90721361f25cc1db793.jpg" type="image/jpeg" length="0"/>
        </item>
      </channel>
    </rss>